so I was thinking about the meta suitor
just going through that there's quite a
lot in it actually but yeah so we can
stop forever he was right so we have
first my first it begins with what
should be done by one skillful and good
hmm sighs to gain the state of peace
it's kind of a question really well
where we spoke before only the person
with the right view no as good as good
and bad as bad knows crystallize Kucera
and aqua so as a crew saw which means
they also to fly somebody in the review
what should be done once you know coucil
exclusive and aku salazar kuzava one who
is skillful in good yes one who knows
good is good that is bad
what should he do to have his mind in a
peaceful state says let him be able
upright and straight forward already
what is always room for improvement
so the banner is upright and straight
forward from petitioners point of view
but not from an arrogant point of view
because it is easy to speak to gentle
and not proud and this gentle company
as much he's not sensitive yes now
that's our gentle is like you are non
gentle when you have intentions of harm
if you are unable to have in a to act
out of intentions of harm you gentle
that doesn't mean you will necessarily
come across his is kind and gentle
because people don't have criteria for
virtually kind and gentle is more proud
except not a problem you cannot be
rooted in your vanity in your conceit
he is contented easily easy to support
easily satisfied with few tasks and
living very lightly hmm his faculties
are serene schewe
or serene prudent and modest hmm unbusy
unswayed by the emotions of the cleanse
so unswayed hmm but the emotions of
others of others you of other
authorities of other traditions or other
establishments when you say are them the
rules of a clan means I if you belong to
it you must obey by that so it's like
belonging to a greater identity which is
usually everybody does belongs to some
greater identity to some extent big
culture religion education or something
makes you belong to the to that group
identity but that actually requires the
wrong view it's rooted in the wrong view
that kind of belonging it's rooted in
you not being transparent in regard to
your own individuality so the one who
has the right view who has developed his
mind he cannot tend ignore the fact that
he always remains enclosed within
himself so then if he chooses to follow
but client says you should do he will
only do so because he knows good is good
and bad
not because the clan said so but if you
don't know for yourself you will be
going and by the words of others by the
authority of others by the majority
majority of others exactly that's
another way of oh we'll look I don't
understand this I don't understand that
but this is more numerous there's more
people saying this than that so I'll
just go with the majority on this one
means either way you don't understand
for yourself so even say if their
majority were right you are in the wrong
because you're not understanding for
itself you're going just by the majority
of it you being swayed by you've got no
grounding yours no ground you just it's
a circumstantial circumstantially
occurred that in this instance majority
was right and but you as a rule of thumb
go with the majority out of your own
weakness and basically lack of
understanding that's why literally like for sotapanna
that's why literally like for sotapanna
and he develops the right view when he
knows kusa let's go solo acoustic scusa
so to say even if the whole world would
say the buddha was wrong or that's wrong
if he knows that is right he would go
with what he knows is right now from
petitioners point of view that sounds
like an extremely arrogant and proud
position who do you think you are you
know better than the entire world but
it's factually he knows better than the
entire world mean that's what solar pond
is they doesn't just think he knows
better the entire world in his thoughts
are not rooted in I am better than the
entire world I am worse or umeko his
thoughts are rooted in recognizing cuzco
as acasola cassava coucil as cassava aku
salazar Cuusoo so wholesome is wholesome
unwholesome is unwholesome so if the
whole world says this is unwholesome but
he knows that to be wholesome he will
not go with the entire book if the whole
world says yes this is wholesome and he
knows that is also he'll go with it
because it wholesome not because the
entire world said so so that's how he
will not be swayed by what clients say
to do because he has done internal
criteria which is and you will never
develop that into internal criteria if
you never basically
look beyond and make effort to
understand things for yourself on that
individual basis but instead always seek
shelter in the safety of numbers crowd
traditions Authority which is a whole
column suta do not go by the majority
for its own sake by the tradition find
out for yourself and many people kind of
think they understand that oh yes of
course find out for myself experience
for myself personal truth yet when it
comes to that drilling their views down
it's gonna be well most people say this
that's why I'm right because I just
subscribed to whatever else people say
yeah but we understand that as right
because it's right or do you just
basically seek the safety in the group
and if you do you'll never develop the
right view or have a peaceful mind well
you will not have a peaceful mind
without it I believe yes there is no
peace without understanding there is an
understanding without a right view there
is safety in numbers by the way it's not
that the safety you get from the group
or majority of belonging to a tradition
or a group identity it's not that it's
not safe it's not it's not real it is
but it's flawed so it's not a true
safety it's not a safety that you seek
so it's only something that sort of
closest to safety that you know but if
you look at it properly investigate it
you realize actually it's not a safety
it's safety of ignorance doesn't matter
what the size of the group is the fact
is I don't know for myself
they will they say it's right thus each
of the level of my choosing to believe
that they are right because it makes me
feel comfortable it's also happen to be
why it's all secular it's all secondary
yeah exactly yeah I mean you can find
the right group the group of our hands
but if you seek the shelter of this if
you seek the safety basically and and
follow what they say just so you'll be
safe not because you you understood it
you won't be safe so you can live with
the Buddha himself and you'll still be a
particular because you're not allowing
it basically to penetrate on the levels
it should which isn't that individual
basis of recognition of fundamental not
safety non-safety fundamental exposure
of existence fundamental impermanence
fear and all of that now it's always why
people go with it even if you know often
you saw that like in the living in the
various monasteries and stuff people
would but sometimes follow or come
having been following certain teachings
that they know themselves but not
adequate because they've been doing for
20 years and still haven't overcome
things that even they made them start
practicing but they couldn't give it up
because there is nothing else left which
means they would have to them except
their individual responsibility for that
exposure and not knowing so although
they know the teachings they've been
following were not adequate they're
still too afraid to admit that to
themselves so that's what I call he
didn't work for me but have you
understood it or no have you you made
the effort to understand so what did you
do what extended unit you must have some
understanding if you recognize that it
doesn't work for you what is that
understanding why doesn't work for you
is it because it's inadequate so already
have a sense of all this is inadequate
but you're still afraid to take
responsibility for that own recognition
and instead I'll just pretend and ignore
the inadequacy so I can still take in
the safety of numbers safety of
tradition safety an established norm and
so on safety of the meditation method
yeah comfort zone oh Jesus I kind of at
the back home I know that he hasn't
resulted in things I was hoping you
would help doesn't result in things that
the so to say to result but yes it it's
less uncomfortable then if I'll go
against it and and do away with it
feel less exposed if you pretend there
is a problem so unswayed by the emotions
of my friends hmm and let him never do
the slightest thing but otherwise men
might hold so the wise men so the other
men we drive view with hope lame so what
is blamable wrong he is the most
blameworthy thing so let him not
entertain wrong with you in any extent
in regard to anything even for a second
because that's the most plain water
thing but other killing stealing
cheating lying all wise men agree that
is unwholesome and you know for yourself
is unwholesome now you might not
necessarily at that stage you might not
necessarily see sensuality is directly
unwholesome but by the extension of the
principles you have understood by the
extension of that wisdom you can safely
assume that its most likely unwholesome
and then act accordingly and restrain
yourself and then you will come to
realize that it wasn't wholesome
velocity isn't least he's not swayed by
the motion of the clan but he little
listens to them oh yeah exactly because
he's not conceited yeah he does not
dismiss the clans because he is
self-centered and proud he's not swayed
by their motions doesn't mean he has no
perspective on their emotion which
equally then means he will also have
perspective on that which is factual
wisdom so even if somebody does not
belong to the clan he approves off or he
was born with or brought up with he
would recognize when somebody says
something that is correct that is along
the principle of kousouris Kucera
arcosolia who surah so he with
recognized wisdom in others but I don't
mean from from a point of view of a
petitioner without the right view that
sounds like the most conceited thing all
the teachers say this all the Buddhist
tradition say this who do you think you
are saying the opposite now sure it is
possible that one who is saying the
opposite might be doing simply because
he's so conceited
so you just wants to go against
everybody else but then you listen what
else that person has to say is it just a
man rent or are they making sense in
other regards as well then you realize
oh well they are which means even if the
whole world says one thing there is
something to this so maybe it's worth
investigating it's certainly not worth
dismissing it just because majority does
not agree with it I mean mentally there
is only one Buddha in the world when it
arises there are no two Buddhas it's
impossible to be at the same time which
means the Buddha is as alone as it gets
he is the only the first soul being
that's against the grain of the entire
universe not just this world
and yeah when that man met him straight
out to his enlightenment and said we
look so calm who was teaching it you
follow because this man assumed you must
follow someone some tradition some
observance some tradition and it would
effectually said I follow no one's
teaching on my own guard I'm the supreme
leader of men pure facts but how did
this man take it all right so be it good
for you and walked off he did not
believe him and he thought look it is
considered something that should not be
a criteria yeah he might be he might
have been factually say a person who
declares that manufactory conceited or
just just sort of being argumentative
just going against whatever likes
tearing things up but then you listen
what else they have to say and then
you'll see oh wait there is something
more to this it's not that they're just
negating they're providing reasons for
the negating they're providing rational
explanations the tie-in with other
things that you know could be
interpreted that way and if that's the
case then you should investigate it
further and then use that as a criterion
not because oh 100 people say one thing
and one person says the other thus he's
wrong and sometimes people even know
that person in in in minority is not
wrong but I still try to argue point
that you should still go with the
majority and not disturb the established
order of majority that is true only when
the if when non disturbing of the
established order of the clans of the
tradition would not go against the
message you have so if you can go with
the order without compromising the
message that you have which is against
what the orders message is then it's
fine you can go with the order but if
you can if going with the order means
compromising the message that you have
that is correct
that the whole order disagrees with then
you shouldn't go videoed you should
stick with
because well that's the only thing that
matters right view wrong the wrong view
is the Buddha said is the most blame
worldly thing more blame voted in
killing stealing cheating in everything
else it's the utmost single blame worthy
it's the utmost single blame worthy
thing in the entire universe in entire
sense our thinking to know that which
you don't holding on to a view without
questioning it without understanding it
because it goes to becomes bit different
this so let's talk about what this
person should be thinking hmm in terms
of that meta peaceful mind he said let
him think in safety and in happiness may
creatures all be of a heavy mind
hmm whatever breathing beings they may
be matter what they are yeah may
creatures all be overhead mind
did no one work for another's undoing or
even slight him at all anywhere I never
let them wish each other ill and so so
is this this is what he should be
thinking yes on the level of your
thoughts do not entertain even slightest
like negative animosity your will and so
on even that doesn't matter
doesn't matter what happens to you
doesn't matter on account of what things
happen to you doesn't matter from whom
from what type of being don't have
limited mind towards them but if you
because most people take this to say
okay this is the mantra hmm then I must
now say a million times a million times
in safety and this might make creatures
yeah
you do that do that do it well you ask
yourself does repeating a mantra
cultivate maintain in the standing of
the point of that mantra what is it
actually quite the opposite and focusing
on repeating the mantra means ignoring
the fact that it needs to be understood
because if you so if you had to I
remember doing similar thing hmm
for what longer repeating certain yeah
certain phrases may my mother be well on
me yes sister this may I be this that
that and you generate it's quite
pleasant thought hmm and you have
Pleasant feelings and you feel good yeah
just feel yeah but that's not what he
says he says you should cultivate that
mind the state of mind that has no
animosity towards anything bleeding of
any kind and you don't go through it
state of mind by repeating the random
words because if that would be the case
the Buddha would have said so just run
this and you'll be purified yet whenever
he talked about it he talked about it in
a dismissive manner of the other
romantic traditions they were doing and
he would criticize him for chanting
vendors without understanding what
they're chanting so they're just
parroting basically the verses cuz they
develop the belief that the verses in
themselves carry magic of purification
and then he said that even the original
brahmins that sort of compile those
Vedas and the wisdom in them they
actually understood that that's why they
were bored he meant Brahmans of the old
day they understood the versus the
understood the meaning they were not
just chanting them so if you chant for
the sake of remembering it for the sake
of them reflecting on it to understand
it of course but if you chant because
you believe that chanting purifies is
you and maintains your mind of no meal
will that's utterly completely wrong you
said lucky these peoples say this no I
will say that as well
yeah and that's how I will partake in
that if I'm saying a minute so I will
just go by the hearsay tradition and
repeating words of others by merely
repeating words of others I will purify
myself that's basically practically what
their view is for those who believe that
just chanting will purify but let him
think let him to think about this let me
reflect upon it they reflect letting
develop the state of mind that is
limitless that that includes all these things you
that that includes all these things you
can have animosity towards so you
develop a state of mind free from
animosity that's all the things within
that be you could hate you cannot hate
because hate is roots in the state of
mind not in things that you hate so you
can also ask yeah you think about it in
safety and in happiness my creatures all
be yeah I'll think about those verses
about guidelines for your computer can't
imagine why why do it okay so the buddha
said nothing they breathe why is that or
if you can't figure out why take the
Buddhist world and Trust then figure out
how to achieve it so how will I have us
one state of mind
they will not hate this wide array of
diverse beings and objects is that
achievable by chasing down the diversity
of the objects or is it achievable by
maintaining the uniformity of one non
hateful mind which is more likely is it
about cultivating the pleasure of a
particular thoughts mmm-hmm and the
voice of the displeasure another
particular version of thought yeah or is
it cultivating a thought that is above
either a pleasure or displeasure
exactly the continues and just as a
mother with her life protects her any
child so let him then for every living thing
so let him then for every living thing
protect his boundless mind so we spoke
about it before mums later it's quite
obvious you have contemporary
translations that skew that and they
basically imply that as the mother
protects a child you protect all these
living beings does it so let him protect
every living being like his own child it
says let him protect his one mind like a
mother protects one child one son
literally cuz your only son that's your
only that you mind your mind is your
only child so you will not forget about
cultivation protection and maintenance
of that child because if you do it could
die and it could result in your own
death so if you protect your mind as
your own child you will automatically
protect all living beings because when
there is action of non protection of all
living beings it's not rooted in those
beings or non those beats rooting in
your mind of your will so if you protect
your mind from your will enough no
active ill will can be exercised towards
anything in the world
so by proxy then you protect the entire
world and that's how they would explain
other hunt by practicing for his own
benefit practices for the benefit of the
whole universe yeah we want it yeah if
you want to see no but most people that
internal transparent dimension is is not
transparent it's they don't see it so they measure
it's they don't see it so they measure
goodness or or non goodness by the level
of engagement with others and with the
world so from that point of view of an
ignorant autogenous view our hunt is the
most selfish person in the world swayed
by the emotions
yes where are the emotions of others
exactly you Zebrahead
using the measure of emotion
for whether things are good or bad this
makes us real good thus it's good yeah
and you see I'd only clear then many
people approached the Dhamma practice
rooted in that our practice freedom from
my dependence on feelings by following
what makes me feel good that's a
contradiction in terms
that's what we said that in the previous
one of the previous talks I don't
remember what all that was Sheldon but
if you just you don't need to practice
the kindness and nominal world towards
the world thought about any one in
particular just practice it towards
whatever present feeling is enduring in
your experience and you cover the entire
world anything to breathe
you cannot hate because you stop
resisting the discomfortable feeling
just present in doing anything surely
want to help that's the only way you
know can have a desire to help but you
can choose to ignore understanding what
is truly helpful on account of that
desire or you can choose to not ignore
and make the effort to understand what
is truly helpful so what is truly
helpful is the mind of no ill will
and if you could do that then you can
potentially teach others to do this of
course which protects them yeah because
you can build people houses food food
that's all Monday Monday
pertaining to the world the Netherlands
is not there you can do that if that's
you go but you can't expect to do that
and practice dumb at the same time
because those goals are mutually
exclusive if you can help others and not
compromise the lifestyle that's
dedicated to practice in the Dhamma that
you understood that's fine of course
somebody's drowning you pull them out
then Allah will teach the Dhamma in
these three seconds before they drown
but if you dedicate your life to saving
people from drowning in those particular
instances and on account of that neglect
your own mind your own child of non your
will well that's doesn't have anyone
that the help is very limited very
fleeting yes not substantial above below
and all around untroubled with no enemy
and while he stands walks sits or lies
down hmm
free from drowsiness let him resolve
upon this mindfulness yep this is the
peaceful life yes
you cannot resolve upon things that are
not clear
like this instances in the suitors of if
a person who becomes an adamant by
resolving upon wisdom so he resolves
upon that which he came inside with
wisdom so in order to resolve upon
something you need to know what that is
you need to be clear about you need to
be familiar with it
you need to have made the effort to
remove any opaqueness and ambiguity in
regard to the meaning and nature of it
once it's sufficiently clear that's when
that resolve can occur and that's when
you can maintain that resolve and that's
why can result in a township is it free
from drowsiness but people free from
sloths free from lack of clarity free
from laziness in regard to maintaining
the clarity months somehow energetic
like magical energy or free from he's
not tired he's got this abundant energy
flowing through his body
yeah no it's not he even refers to the
clarity of the meaning yeah which is why
you can dissolve a pony with mindfulness
not this energy of you can be tired but
tiredness does not induce losing the
sight of the right context does not
induce forgetting about your only child
you're tired but you still clear about
what's important you're still clear
about what you must protect used to
protect it and when you're not I'll you
protect it even more you cultivate
the last verses he when he when he has
[Applause] when he's not holding to any views hmm
when he's not holding to any views hmm
his virtuous and has perfected seen and
purges greed from for sensual desires he
should not hold into wrong news they are
not talking to wrong views virtuous
perfect in all engines free from sensual
desires he no longer get out of hand
become he goes beyond the views that's
what it means well so you need the right
view in order to overcome the wrong
views but for another hunt basically he
overcomes even the right view
that's that suitor has the Noble
Eightfold Path and foreign and it's like
a 10 fold path whereby he overcomes even
that dependence on the view the right
view the right criteria
he even extinguishes that sorry resolve
on clarity with the right view yeah you
maintain it you cultivate it until it
ripens and then even that falls off yeah
it's like once you use the raft that you
built you cross the shore and then leave
the raft and when do you leave the raft
well you know when you're safe on the
other side of the show it's like halfway
through pedaling oh do I abandon raft
now or yeah you cannot doubt it because
it's not up to you anymore you Chris
they say that you abandon this raft and
get it I'll sure that's all abandoned
now right right right yeah I'll
preemptively abandon it because you
shouldn't hold on to anything yeah yeah
no then that's often misunderstood I
know in the same like the contemporary
chanting of that that not hold to any
views or they even now I think since in
some translation don't hold to fix the
views there's like well that's a fixed
view I should not hold to fix views is
your fixed view and there is no way out
of that except finding the right type of
fixed view which is the fixed view of
soda ban that he developed to
understanding the Buddhist teaching then
using that fixed view to overcome all
the kind of underlying tendencies and
kilesas and so on
that fixed view will wither away as well
and that's when you do not hunt but
people think oh if I abstain from
declaring my view I've somehow scaled
between the views and I will be free
from the views by not holding on to
views which is the view that I hold so
that last verse refers to the other
handshape so the only one truly who can
say I don't hold 20 views anymore is the
one whose right view has withered away
extinguished itself through the right
effort so you won't be on the views
yeah that's the full development
yeah it's not a choice but it's not so
they're gonna makes a choice I will not
hold to my right view and he becomes
another honey it's a result of the right
practice then the Buddha outlines there
and then says if you practice like that
you will not anymore
the attach to any view even the right
view you will be another on that but
it's the right view they brought in
there it's the raft they took in to the
other Shore